KUNG FU PANDA
片名：功夫熊猫
Legend tells of a legendary warrior...
传说中有位传奇大侠
...whose kung fu skills were the stuff of legend.
他的传奇功夫出神入化
He traveled the land in search of worthy foes.
他云游四方，寻找比得上他的对手
I see you like to chew. Maybe you should chew on my fist!
我看你还挺爱吃，有本事吃我一拳！
The warrior said nothing, for his mouth was full.
大侠沉默片刻，因为嘴里还塞满吃的
Then he swallowed. And then he spoke.
等他咽了下去，就开口了
Enough talk. Let's fight!
少说废话，出手吧！
Shashabooey!
拿命来！
He was so deadly in fact,
他的招式凶猛炫丽
that his enemies would go blind from over exposure to pure awesomeness.
敌人看多了炫招都能双目失明！
- My eyes! - He's too awesome!
- 我看不见了！ - 他太炫了！
- And attractive. - How can we repay you?
- 也好帅啊 - 我们该如何报答你？
There is no charge for awesomeness.
凶猛帅气本是天生
Or attractiveness.
不求回报！
Kablooey!
小宇宙爆发！
It mattered not how many foes he faced,
不管面对多少敌人
They were no match for his bodacity!
他们全都不是对手
Never before had a panda been so feared! And so loved.
从没有熊猫这样被人惧怕，又被人喜爱
Even the most heroic heroes in all of China,
就连中国的盖世英雄
the Furious Five,
虎胆五侠
bowed in respect to this great master.
也拜倒在绝世大师之下
We should hang out.
咱们乐乐去？
Agreed.
正合我意
But hanging out would have to wait.
可休闲时间得等等了
Because when you're facing the 10,000 demons of Demon Mountain,
因为当面对恶魔山的一万大军时
there's only one thing that matters and that's...
只有一件事情最重要，那就是⋯
Po! Get up!
阿宝！起床了！
You'll be later for work!
要赶不上干活了！
What?
啥？？
Po! Get up!
阿宝！起床了
Po. What are you doing up there?
阿宝，你在那儿折腾啥呢？
Nothing.
没什么
Monkey! Mantis! Crane! Viper! Tigress!
金猴！螳螂！仙鹤！灵蛇！娇虎！
Po! Let's go! You're late for work.
阿宝！快过来！都已经开工了
Coming!
就来！
Sorry, Dad.
抱歉，老爸
Sorry doesn't make the noodles.
光说抱歉可做不了面条
What were you doing up there? All that noise.
你在上面干什么着？那么多动静
Nothing. I just had a crazy dream.
没啥，就是做了个怪梦
About what?
什么梦？
What were you dreaming about?
梦见什么了？
What was I?
梦见什么？
I was dreaming about...
我梦见了⋯
...noodles.
面条
Noodles? You were really dreaming about noodles?
面条？你真的梦见面条了？
Yeah. What else would I be dreaming about?
是啊，我还能梦见啥
Careful! That soup is sharp.
小心！那汤⋯扎嘴
Oh, happy day!
今天真吉利！
My son, finally having the noodle dream!
我儿子总算梦到面条了！
You don't know how long I've been waiting for this moment.
你不知道我等这等了多久了
This is a sign, Po.
这是个好兆头，阿宝
A sign of what?
什么兆头？
You are almost ready to be entrusted with the secret ingredient of my Secret Ingredient Soup.
你就快准备好继承咱家的秘方鲜汤的秘方了！
Then you will fulfill your destiny and take over the restaurant!
然后你就能履行使命，继承面馆！
Just as I took it over from my father, who took it over from his father...
就像我从父亲手里接过来 他从我爷爷手里接过来
...who won it from a friend in mahjong.
我爷爷跟朋友打麻将赢下来
Dad, Dad, Dad, it was just a dream.
爸爸，爸爸，这不过是个梦啊
No, it was the dream.
不，这可是远大梦想
We are noodle folk. Broth runs through our veins.
我们是做面条的，血脉里流淌着汤汁
But, Dad, didn't you ever, I don't know, want to do something else?
可爸爸，你就没想过做点别的？
Something besides noodles?
除了面条之类的？
Actually, when I was young and crazy,
其实我年少轻狂时
I thought about running away and learning how to make tofu.
曾经想过逃跑，去学做豆腐
So why didn't you?
那怎么没去？
Because it was a stupid dream.
因为这是痴人说梦！
Can you imagine me making tofu?
你能想象我做豆腐啥样？
Tofu.
豆腐⋯
No! We all have our place in this world.
不，咱们在世上都有自己的位置
Mine is here, and yours is...
我的是在这儿，你的⋯
I know, is here.
我知道，也是这儿
No, it's at tables 2, 5, 7, and 12
不，是2号5号12号桌
Service with a smile.
记得要微笑服务
Well done, students... if you were trying to disappoint me.
干得不错徒弟们，要是你们想要让我失望的话
Tigress, you need more ferocity! Monkey, greater speed.
娇虎你不够凶猛，金猴你不够快
Crane, height. Viper, subtlety. Mantis...
仙鹤飞得不够高，灵蛇不够敏捷，螳螂⋯
- Master Shifu. - What?!
- 功夫大师 - 什么？！
It's Master Oogway. He wants to see you.
是乌龟大师，他想见你
Master Oogway, you summoned me? Is something wrong?
乌龟大师，你想见我？有什么事吗
Why must something be wrong for me to want to see my old friend?
想见老朋友非要有事吗？
So, nothing's wrong?
那就是没事了？
Well, I didn't say that.
我也没这么说
You were saying?
您的意思是？
I have had a vision.
我有一个预感
Tai Lung will return.
大龙会杀回来
That is impossible! He is in prison.
这不可能，他还在大牢里
Nothing is impossible.
一切皆有可能
Zeng!
小善！
Fly to Chorh-Gom prison
飞去昌高监狱
and tell them to double the guards, double their weapons, double everything!
告诉他们兵力加倍！武器加倍！能加倍的都加倍
Tai Lung does not leave that prison!
不能让大龙逃出来！
Yes, Master Shifu!
是，师傅！
One often meets his destiny on the road he takes to avoid it.
逆天行命，反促因果
We must do something! We can't let him march on the valley, take his revenge!
可我们总得做点什么！不能让他杀回来⋯
He'll... Your mind is like this water, my friend.
他会⋯心如池水，老朋友
When it is agitated, it becomes difficult to see.
随风乍起，自然不易明辨
But if you allow it to settle...
而若水波不兴
...the answer becomes clear.
自然心静则明
The Dragon Scroll.
神龙秘籍
It is time.
是时候了
But who? Who is worthy to be trusted with the secret to limitless power?
可选谁呢？能把这无限神功托付给谁呢？
To become the Dragon Warrior?
谁能成为⋯神龙大侠？
I don't know.
我也不知道
Excuse me. Pardon me. Sorry.
不好意思，抱歉
Watch it! Po
阿宝看着点！
Sorry. Suck it up!
不好意思，收腹！
Sorry. A thousand pardons.
万分抱歉！
What?
什么？
(The Notice)
（虎胆五侠 五时开始）
Master Oogway's choosing the Dragon Warrior! Today!
乌龟大师要选神龙大侠！就今天！
Everyone! Get to the Jade Palace! One of the Five is gonna get the Dragon Scroll!
大伙们，快去翡翠宫！ 虎胆五侠里会有人拿到神龙秘籍！
We've waited 1,000 years for this! Just take the bowl!
千年等一回啊！带着碗去！
This is the greatest day in kung fu history! Don't worry about it, Just go!
这可是功夫史上的大事，快去！
Po! Where are you going?
阿宝！你要去哪儿啊？
To the Jade Palace.
我去⋯翡翠宫
But you're forgetting your noodle cart.
你忘了你的面条小车了
The whole valley will be there, and you'll sell noodles to all of them.
全山谷的人都会去，人手一碗面条可就赚了
Selling noodles?
又卖面条？
But, Dad, you know I was kind of thinking, maybe I...
可爸爸，我在想，也许我⋯
- Yeah? - I was thinking maybe I...
- 嗯？ - 我在想也许我⋯
...could also sell the bean buns. They're about to go bad.
还能卖点豆沙包，都要发霉了
That's my boy!
真是好儿子！
I told you that dream was a sign.
我都说过那梦是个好兆头
Yeah. Glad I had it.
是啊，美梦一场
- I'm a kung fu warrior! - Me, too!
- 我是功夫大侠！ - 我也是
- There's spots at the top. - Let's go.
- 顶上有地方看 - 咱们走
Come on. Come on!
加把劲！加把劲！
Almost there.
就快到了
What?
啥？
No! Oh, no!
噢，不！
- Sorry, Po. - We'll bring you back a souvenir.
- 阿宝你真可怜 - 我们会给你带个纪念品
No. I'll bring me back a souvenir.
不行，我得亲自留一个
It is an historic day.
今天意义非凡
Isn't it, Master Oogway?
不是吗，乌龟大师？
Yes, and one I feared I would not live to see.
是啊，我还担心我活不到今天
Are your students ready?
你的徒弟都准备好了？
Yes, Master Oogway.
是的，乌龟大师
Know this, old friend.
你得明白，老朋友
Whomever I choose will not only bring peace to the valley...
不管我选中谁，都能给山谷带来安宁
...but also to you.
也能把安宁带给你
Let the tournament begin!
比武大会现在开始！
No, no, wait!
不，不，等等！
I'm coming! Wait, wait!
我来了，等等我
Yes!
就来！
Hey! Open the door!
嘿！快开门！
Let me in!
让我进去！
Citizens of the Valley of Peace,
和平谷的居民们
it is my great honor to present to you... Tigress!
我很荣幸向你们介绍⋯娇虎！
Viper! Crane! Monkey! Mantis!
灵蛇！仙鹤！金猴！螳螂！
The Furious Five!
虎胆五侠！
Yeah, the Furious Five!
啊，虎胆五侠！
Warriors, prepare!
勇士们准备！
Wait. No. Oh, peeky-hole.
等等啊，我从小孔偷看吧
- Ready for battle! - Yeah.
- 准备战斗 - 好啊
The Thousand Tongues of Fire.
千条火舌
Look at that.
瞧瞧啊
Hey! Get out of the way!
嘿！快让开
And finally Master Tigress!
最后是娇虎大侠
And believe me, citizens, you have not seen anything yet.
相信我乡亲们，你们还没见识真格的呢
I know!
是没见到！
Master Tigress! Face Iron Ox and his Blades of Death.
娇虎大侠，面对铁牛和死亡之斧
I sense the Dragon Warrior is among us.
我感到神龙大侠就在我们中间
Citizens of the Valley of Peace,
和平谷的乡亲们
Master Oogway will now choose the Dragon Warrior!
乌龟大师现在要选出神龙大侠！
Oh, no! No, no, wait!
啊，别呀，等等！
Yeah.
就这了
Po!
阿宝！
What are you doing?!
你这是在干嘛？
What does it look like I'm doing?! Stop!
你看像在干嘛？！快停下！
I'm going to see the Dragon Warrior!
我要去看神龙大侠！
But I don't understand. You finally had the noodle dream!
可我不明白啊，你总算梦着面条了啊
I lied. I don't dream about noodles, Dad.
我撒谎了，我没梦见什么面条
I love kung fu!
我爱⋯⋯功⋯⋯夫！
Come on, son. Let's get back to work.
行了，儿子，咱们回去干活吧
OK.
好吧
Come back!
回来！
What's going on?
怎么回事？
Where?
这是在哪儿？
What are you pointing?
你指着我干什么？
OK. Sorry.
噢，对不起
I just wanted to see who the Dragon Warrior was.
我只是想来看看神龙大侠
How interesting.
真有意思
Master, are you pointing at me?
大师，您指的是我吗？
- Him. - Who?
- 是他 - 谁？
- You. - Me?
- 你 - 我？
The universe has brought us the Dragon Warrior!
上苍给我们送来了⋯神龙大侠！
- What? - What?!
- 什么？ - 什么？！
- What?! - What?!
- 什么？！ - 什么？！
Stop, wait! Who told you to?
停下，等等！谁让你们这么干的？
Master Oogway, wait.
乌龟大师，等等
That flabby panda can't possibly be the answer to our problem.
那个虚胖的熊猫不可能解决咱们的问题
You were about to point at Tigress and that thing fell in front of her!
你本来要指娇虎的，这东西从天而降
That was just an accident!
这纯粹是个意外
There are no accidents.
从来就没有意外
Forgive us, Master. We have failed you.
请原谅师傅，我们辜负了您
No. If the panda has not quit by morning
不，要是到了早上那熊猫还不走
then I will have failed you.
就是我辜负了你们
Wait! Wait, wait, wait! I bring a message...
等等，等等！我带来了⋯
...from Master Shifu.
功夫大师的信
What?!
什么？！
"Double the guard?!"
“加强兵力？！”
"Extra precautions?!"
“特别防守？！”
"Your prison may not be adequate?!"
“你的监狱也许不够坚固” （画面上是中文）
You doubt my prison security?!
你敢怀疑我的监狱不安全？
Absolutely not.
小的不敢
Shifu does. I'm just the messenger.
是师傅怀疑，我只是个送信的
I'll give you a message for your Master Shifu.
那你替我送信给你那个师傅
Escape from Chorh-Gom prison is impossible!
想从昌高监狱逃走是不可能的
Impressive, isn't it?
很壮观吧？
It's very impressive.
非常壮观
相当壮观
One way in, one way out.
一个口进，一个口出
One thousand guards and one prisoner.
一千名守卫，看守一名囚犯
Yes, except that prisoner...
是啊，只不过这个囚犯是⋯
...is Tai Lung.
大龙
Take us down.
放我们下去
What are you doing?
你要干什么？
Oh, my.
噢，我的天
Behold Tai Lung.
看吧，大龙
I'm just gonna wait right here.
我就在这儿等着好了
It's nothing to worry about. It's perfectly safe.
没什么可担心的，非常安全
Crossbows! At the ready!
弩弓手！准备
Crossbows?
弩弓手？
Hey, tough guy, did you hear?
硬汉，听说了吗？
Oogway's giving someone the Dragon Scroll, and it's not gonna be you.
乌龟把神龙秘籍送人了，而且不是给你
What are you ding? Don't get him mad.
别惹他生气啊
What's he gonna do about it? I've got him completely immobilized.
他又能怎么样？我已经让他动弹不得了
Did I step on the wittle kitty's tail?
我踩到小猫猫的尾巴了？
I'm good. I've seen enough.
行了，我看够了
I'll tell Shifu he has nothing to worry about.
我去告诉师傅没什么可担心的
No, he doesn't.
是啊，瞎担心
I'll tell him that.
我会转告给他
Can we please go now?
现在总可以走了吗？
Dragon Warrior! Dragon Warrior!
神龙大侠！神龙大侠！
Wait a second!
等一下！
I think there's been a slight mistake. Everyone seems to think that I'm...
我觉得好像有点误会，大伙都以为我是⋯
The Sacred Hall of Warriors! No way!
这是勇士圣殿！没搞错吧
Look at this place.
瞧瞧这地方
Master Flying Rhino's armor, with authentic battle damage!
飞天犀牛大师的盔甲，还带着战斗伤痕！
The Sword of Heroes!
这是英雄宝剑！
Said to be so sharp you can cut yourself just by looking.
据说绝对锋利，连看一眼都会被割伤⋯
The Invisible Trident of Destiny!
隐形天命三叉戟！
I've only seen paintings of that painting.
我只见过这宝画的冒牌货
No!
不会吧！
The legendary Urn of Whispering Warriors.
低语武士的神奇灵坛
Said to contain the souls of the entire Tenshu Army.
听说装着整个天蜀大军的灵魂
Hello.
有人吗
Have you finished sight-seeing?
参观结束了吧？
Sorry, I should have come to you first.
对不起，我应该先来看你的
My patience is wearing thin.
我的忍耐可是有限的
Well, I mean, it's not like you were going anywhere.
哦，那个，你好像着急也去不了哪儿啊
- Would you turn around? - Sure.
- 你转过身 - 好啊
How's it going?
你好啊
How do you get 5,000... Master Shifu!
是怎么把五千个⋯是师傅！
Someone... broke that.
有人⋯把它打坏了
But I'll fix it. Do you have some...
可我会弄好的，你有⋯
...glue?
胶水吗？
A splinter.
扎手了
So you're the legendary Dragon Warrior?
你就是传说中的神龙大侠？
- I guess so. - Wrong!
- 我猜是吧 - 错！
You are not the Dragon Warrior. You will never be the Dragon Warrior until...
你不是神龙大侠，也永远别想成为神龙大侠
...you have learned the secret of the Dragon Scroll.
除非你掌握了这神龙秘籍
So, how does this work?
那，我该怎么着？
Do you have a ladder, or a trampoline, or?
你有没有梯子，或是蹦床什么的？
You think it's that easy? That I'll just hand you the secret
你以为就这么简单？这样拱手把无限神功
- to limitless power? - No, I...
- 白送给你？ - 不，我⋯
One must first master the highest level of kung fu.
要先达到功夫的最高境界
And that is clearly impossible if that one is someone like you.
可像你这样的显然不行
Someone like me?
像我这样的？
Yes, look at you! This fat butt! Flabby arms!
是啊，瞧瞧你！屁股肥大，胳膊松软！
Those are sensitive in the flabby parts.
人家这块肉最怕疼
And this ridiculous belly.
肚子大得离谱
And utter disregard for personal hygiene.
完全不注意个人卫生
Now, wait a minute. That's uncalled for.
你等等，说这话可没必要
Don't stand that close. I can smell your breath.
离得这么近都能闻见你的口臭了
Listen, Oogway said I was...
听着，乌龟说我是⋯
The Wuxi Finger Hold. Not the Wuxi Finger Hold!
五溪劫指扣！别用五溪劫指扣！
Oh, you know this hold?
你知道这招？
Developed by Master Wuxi in the Third Dynasty.
五溪大师在秦朝发明的
Then you know what happens when I flex my pinky.
那你一定知道，我收起小指头会怎么样
- No, no! - You know the hardest part of this?
- 别这样！ - 你知道最难办的是什么吗？
The hardest part is cleaning up afterwards.
最难办的是事后清理干净
OK, OK, take it easy.
好了，好了，悠着点儿
Now listen closely, panda.
给我听好了，熊猫
Oogway may have picked you, but when I'm through with you,
乌龟选了你，可你从我这儿领教以后
I promise you, you're going to wish he hadn't! Are we clear?
我向你保证，你会希望他没选你！明白了？
Yeah, we're clear. We're so clear.
是的，明白了，明明白白
Good.
这就好
I can't wait to get started.
我都要等不及了
- Let's begin. - Wait, wait, wait.
- 咱们开始吧 - 等等，等等
What?
说什么？
- Now? - Yes, now.
- 现在？ - 是啊，现在开始
Unless the great Oogway was wrong and you are not the Dragon Warrior.
除非乌龟大师错了，你不是神龙大侠
Oh, OK, well...
噢，好吧
I don't know if I can do all of those moves.
我可不认为那些我都做得到
Well, if we don't try, we'll never know, will we?
不试试怎么知道呢？
Yeah, it's just, maybe we can find something more suited to my level.
啊，就是，咱们可以选个符合我这水平的吗？
What level is that?
你是什么水平？
Well, I'm not a master, but...
反正我不是什么大师，那⋯
...let's just start at zero. Level zero.
咱们就从零开始，没水平
No. There is no such thing as level zero.
你上哪都找不到没水平的
- Maybe I can start with that. - That?
- 要不我从那个开始 - 那个？
We use that for training children and propping the door open when it's hot.
那个是用来训练小孩的，或者天热了顶门的
But if you insist...
可要是你坚持⋯
The Furious Five!
虎胆五侠！
You're so much bigger than your action figures. Except, you, Mantis. You're the same.
你们比玩具娃娃大多了，除了你，螳螂 你差不多一般大
Go ahead, panda. Show us what you can do.
熊猫露一手吧，让我们见识一下
Are they gonna watch, or should I wait till they get back to work?
他们要看着吗？要不等他们去练功了我再试？
Hit it.
出拳吧！
OK, yeah. I mean, I just ate. So I'm still digesting.
我是说，我刚吃饱，还在消化
So my kung fu might not be as good as... later on.
可能我的功夫会⋯打点折扣
Just hit it.
快出拳！
All right.
好啊
What you got? You got nothing, 'cause I got it right here.
你狂什么？别嚣张，因为我站这儿了
You picking on my friends? Get ready to feel thunder.
找我兄弟们的茬？等着接我大招吧
I'm coming at you with crazy feet.
我用无影脚问候你
Come on. I'm a blur. You've never seen bear style.
来啊，我无影无踪，你没见过熊拳吧
You've only seen praying mantis.
你就见过坐盘式螳螂拳
Or monkey style.
或是什么猴拳
Or I could come at you snickety-snake.
要么给你来个蛇拳的藏蛇穿山
Would you hit it!
你快出拳！
All right. All right.
好吧，好吧
Why don't you try again? A little harder.
再试一次，多用点劲儿
How's that?
怎么样？
(tooth)
（牙掉了）
That hurts.
疼啊！
This will be easier than I thought.
赶走他比我想得还轻松
I'm feeling a little nauseous!
晕得我都要吐了！
Those are hard!
这可打疼了
My tenders.
我的鸡鸡
How did I do?
表现如何？
There is now a level zero.
总算见识没水平了
- There's no words. - No denying that.
- 我都无语了 - 可不是嘛
What was Master Oogway thinking?
乌龟大师怎么想的？
The poor guy's gonna get himself killed.
这可怜的家伙把命都得搭上！
He is so mighty!
他好强大！
The Dragon Warrior fell out of the sky on a ball of fire!
神龙大侠，坐着火球从天而降
When he walks, the very ground shakes!
他走一走，地也抖三抖
One would think Master Oogway would choose someone who knew kung fu.
我还以为乌龟大师会选个真懂功夫的人
Yeah, or could at least touch his toes.
怎么着也该够得着脚趾头吧
Or even see his toes.
能看着就不错了
OK.
好的
Great.
这下爽了
Hi. You're up.
你好，你醒了
I am now.
被你吵醒的
I was just...
我刚才⋯
Some day, huh?
这一天真够劲
That kung fu stuff is hard work, right? Are your biceps sore?
功夫那套可是费劲活，你二头肌酸吗？
I've had a long and rather disappointing day, so...
我这一天可是又难熬又失望，所以⋯
Yeah, I should probably get to sleep now.
是啊，我得早点睡了
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. Of course. - OK, thanks.
- 是啊，当然 - 好的，谢了
It's just... Man, I'm such a big fan!
可老兄，我是你们的超级粉丝
You guys were amazing at the Battle of Weeping River.
你们在泣河之战表现神勇
Outnumbered a thousand to one, but you didn't stop. You just...
以一敌千，还毫不惧怕，你们就⋯
Sorry about that.
不好意思啊
Look, you don't belong here.
喂，你不属于这里
I know. I know. You're right.
我知道，我知道，你说得对
I don't have... I just...
我什么都没有⋯我只是⋯
My whole life I dreamed of...
我这辈子就梦想着⋯
No, I meant you don't belong here. I mean, in this room. This is my room.
不，我的意思是你不属于这儿 这个房间，这是我的房间
Property of Crane.
仙鹤房地产
OK. Right, right.
啊，对，是啊
So, you want to get to sleep.
那么你要睡了
- Yeah. - I'm keeping you up.
- 是啊 - 我耽误你睡觉了
We got big things tomorrow.
咱们明天还有大事儿要做
All right. You're awesome. Last thing I'm gonna say. Bye-bye.
好了，你棒极了，就说这些，再见
What was that?
说什么呢？
I didn't say anything.
我什么都没说
OK. All right. Good night.
哦，好，晚安
Sleep well.
睡个好觉
That seemed a little awkward.
刚才可有点尴尬
Master Tigress! I didn't mean to wake you.
娇虎大侠！我没想吵醒你
- You don't belong here. - Yeah, of course.
- 你不属于这里 - 是啊，当然
This is your room.
这是你的房间
I mean, you don't belong in the Jade Palace.
我是说你不属于翡翠宫
You're a disgrace to kung fu, and if you have
你是武林的耻辱
any respect for who we are and what we do,
如果你还尊重我们，尊重武林
you will be gone by morning.
天亮之前趁早离开
close the door
关门
Big fan!
超级粉丝哦！
I see you have found the Sacred Peach Tree of Heavenly Wisdom.
我看你自己找到了这棵天智圣桃树
Is that what this is? Sorry. I thought it was just a regular peach tree.
这是圣桃树？对不起，我还以为是普通的⋯桃树
I understand. You eat when you are upset.
我明白，你心情烦躁就开吃解闷
Upset? I'm not upset. What makes you think I'm upset.
烦躁？我没烦啊，是什么让你这么想
So why are you so upset?
你到底在烦些什么？
I probably sucked more today than anyone in the history of kung fu.
我可能是功夫史上最烂
In the history of China. In the history of sucking!
中国史上最烂，最烂史上最烂的！
Probably.
有可能
And the Five! Man, you should've seen them! They totally hate me.
而那五个，天哪，他们都快恨死我了
Totally.
是恨死了
How is Shifu ever going to turn me into the Dragon Warrior?
师傅究竟怎么样，才能把我变成神龙大侠？
I mean, I'm not like the Five.
我又不像那五个
I've got no claws, no wings, no venom.
我没利爪，也没翅膀，或是毒液
Even Mantis has those... thingies.
就连螳螂都有那些⋯东东
Maybe I should just quit and go back to making noodles.
我看我还是退出算了，回家做面条去
Quit, don't quit.
退出，不退出
Noodles, don't noodles.
做面条，不做面条
You are too concerned with what was and what will be.
你太犹豫不决，又瞻前顾后
There's a saying:
有句话说的好：
Yesterday is history,
昨日已逝
tomorrow is a mystery,
明日未知
but today is a gift.
而今日为金
That is why it is called the present.
这就是为什么叫做“今”日
- Oh, no! - What's happening?!
- 噢，不！ - 怎么了？！
To your battle stations! Go! Go! Go!
快去战斗岗位就位！走！走！走！
Fire crossbows!
发射弩弓！
Fire!
发射
Tai Lung is free! I must warn Shifu.
大龙越狱了，我去告诉师傅
- Not going anywhere! Neither is he! - Let go of me!
- 谁也走不了！他也一样 - 放开我呀
Bring it up!
拉起来！
Wait! Bring it back!
等等，降下来！
- He's coming this way! - He won't get far. Archers!
- 他从这儿上来了 - 他跑不远的，弓箭手！
We're dead. So very, very dead.
我们死定了，这下死翘翘了
Not yet we're not. Now!
还没死呢！发射！
- Can we run now? - Yes.
- 能逃命了吗？ - 是啊⋯
(Commander is killed)
（这是本来镶在犀牛司令鼻子上的）
I'm glad Shifu sent you.
很高兴师傅派你来了
I was beginning to think I'd been forgotten.
我还以为他把我忘了呢
Fly back there and tell them...
飞回去告诉他们
...the real Dragon Warrior is coming home.
真正的神龙大侠回家了
Good morning, Master!
早上好，师傅！
Panda!
熊猫！
Wake up!
快起来！
He's quit.
他放弃了
What do we do now, Master? with the panda gone? Who will be the Dragon Warrior?
熊猫走了我们怎么办？谁来替神龙大侠啊？
All we can do is resume our training and trust that in time,
咱们只要恢复训练，等时候到了
the true Dragon Warrior will be revealed.
神龙大侠自会出来
open the door
开门
What are you doing here?!
你在这儿干什么？
Hi! Good morning, Master!
早上好，师傅！
I thought I'd warm up a little.
我想我可以先热热身
You're stuck.
你卡住了
Stuck? Nah. What? Stuck?
卡住？不可能，啥？卡住？
Nah. This is one of my... Yeah, I'm stuck.
这只是我的一个⋯是啊，我卡住了
- Help him. - Oh, dear.
- 帮帮他 - 天哪
Maybe on three. One, two...
数到三吧，一，二⋯
...three.
三
- Thank you. - Don't mention it.
- 谢谢 - 不用谢了
- No, really, I appreciate... - Ever.
- 真的，非常感谢⋯ - 打住
You actually thought you could learn to do a full split in one night?
你真以为能一夜之间就学会大劈叉？
It takes years to develop one's flexibility!
柔韧性训练就要几年时间
And years longer to apply it in combat!
还要更多年才能用于实战
Put that down!
把那放下！
The only souvenirs we collect here are bloody knuckles and broken bones.
我们这儿收集的纪念品只有伤筋断骨
Yeah! Excellent.
哦也！太帅了！
Let's get started.
咱们开始吧
- Are you ready? - I was born re...
- 准备好了？ - 我天生就准⋯
I'm sorry, brother. I thought you said you were ready.
抱歉，老兄，我还以为你说准备好了
That was awesome! Let's go again!
这可太过瘾了！咱们再来一次！
I've been taking it easy on you, panda. But no more.
我对你手下留情的，熊猫，可现在不会了
Your next opponent will be me.
你现在的对手轮到我了
All right! Yeah, let's go!
好啊！咱们来吧
Step forth.
往前一步
The true path to victory is to find your opponent's weakness...
想要真正获胜，就要攻击你对手的弱点
...and make him suffer for it.
让他因此痛不欲生
Oh, yeah!
噢，爽！
To take his strength and use it against him...
要借力打力
...until he finally falls...
直到他被击倒⋯
...or quits.
或放弃
A real warrior never quits.
一个真正的勇士绝不放弃
Don't worry, Master. I will never quit!
放心吧，师傅，我绝不放弃
If he's smart, he won't come back up those steps.
他要是聪明，就不会爬上来了
But he will.
他会上来的
He's not going to quit, is he?
他不会放弃的，是吗？
He's not going to quit bouncing, I'll tell you that.
我告诉你，他不会放弃翻滚的
I thought you said acupuncture would make me feel better.
不是说针灸能让我好受些吗
Trust me, it will.
听我的没错
It's just not easy finding the right nerve points under all this...
就是不太容易找准穴位，有这么多⋯
- Fat? - Fur. I was going to say fur.
- 肥肉？ - 毛皮，我想要说的是毛皮
Sure you were.
才怪
Who am I to judge a warrior based on his size? Look at me.
咱们不能以大小论英雄，你看我
I'm over here.
我在这儿呢
Maybe you should look at this again.
你还是再看看这个吧
Oh, OK.
噢，对啊
Stop it. Stop!
停手，停下
I know Master Shifu is trying to inspire me and all...
我明白师傅这是在点拨我
...but if I didn't know better, I'd say he was trying to get rid of me.
可要是不了解他，我会以为他想赶我走
I know he can seem kind of heartless...
我知道他看起来铁石心肠
...but he wasn't always like that.
可他以前不是这样
According to legend,
据传说
there was once a time when Master Shifu actually used to smile.
曾经的师傅总是面带微笑
- No! - Yes.
- 瞎说！ - 真的
But that was before.
不过是在那事儿以前
Before what?
什么以前？
Before Tai Lung.
是大龙的事儿
We're not really supposed to talk about him.
我们其实不该去谈论他
Well, if he's going to stay here, he should know.
如果熊猫要留在这儿，他应该知道
Guys, guys, I know about Tai Lung.
伙计们，我知道大龙
He was a student. The first ever to master the thousand scrolls of kung fu.
他是个弟子，第一个掌握了千卷功夫秘籍
And then he turned bad, and now he's in jail.
后来他心眼坏了，现在关在大牢里
He wasn'tjust a student.
他不只是个弟子
Shifu found him as a cub...
他刚生下来，就被师傅捡到了
...and he raised him as his son.
师傅把他当儿子养大
And when the boy showed talent in kung fu...
当大龙显示出功夫天份后
...Shifu trained him.
师傅耐心教导他
He believed in him. He told him he was destined for greatness.
他相信大龙，告诉他注定会成大器
It was never enough for Tai Lung.
而大龙心比天高
He wanted the Dragon Scroll.
他想要神龙秘籍
But Oogway saw darkness in his heart and refused.
可乌龟看出了他内心的阴暗，拒绝了他
Outraged, Tai Lung laid waste to the valley.
暴怒之下，大龙重创和平谷
He tried to take the scroll by force.
他想要抢走秘籍
And Shifu had to destroy what he had created.
师傅也不得不亲自摧毁自己的心血
But how could he?
可又怎么忍心
Shifu loved Tai Lung like he had never loved anyone before.
师傅从没像爱大龙那样爱过任何人
Or since.
以后也一样
And now he has a chance to make things right.
现在他终于有机会弥补过错
To train the true Dragon Warrior.
来训练出真正的神龙大侠
And he's stuck with you.
碰着你这个活宝
A big fat panda who treats it like a joke.
一个大胖熊猫，把训练当儿戏
That is it!
我受够了！
Wait! My fault! I accidentally tweaked his facial nerve.
等等，我的错！我不小心扎到面部神经了
And may have also stopped his heart.
可能碰巧还把心跳弄停了
Inner peace.
静下心来
Inner...
静下⋯
Inner peace.
静下心来
Would whoever is making that flapping sound quiet down?!
在那儿扇巴掌的人给我安静！
Inner...
静下⋯
Oh, Zeng.
噢，是小善啊
Excellent.
正是时候
Excellent, I could use some good news right now.
正好能听些好消息
Master! Master!
大师，大师！
I have... It's... It's very bad news.
我有个⋯是⋯很坏的消息
Shifu.
师傅
There is just news. There is no good or bad.
消息就是消息，岂有好坏十分？
Master, your vision. Your vision was right.
大师，你的预感成真了
Tai Lung has broken out of prison. He's on his way.
大龙越狱了，他就要杀回来了
That is bad news...
还真是坏消息⋯
...if you do not believe that the Dragon Warrior can stop him.
要是你不相信神龙大侠能够阻止的话
The panda? Master, that panda is not the Dragon Warrior.
那个熊猫？大师，他才不是神龙大侠
He wasn't meant to be here! It was an accident.
他本来就不该出现，那是个意外
There are no accidents.
从来就没有意外
Yes, I know. You've said that already.
是啊，你之前说过⋯
- Twice. - Well, that was no accident, either.
- 两遍了 - 那也不是意外
Thrice.
三遍了
My old friend,
我的老朋友
the panda will never fulfill his destiny, nor you yours,
熊猫永远不能完成他的使命，你也一样
until you let go of the illusion of control.
除非你能抛开控制一切的幻想
Illusion?
幻想？
Yes. Look at this tree, Shifu.
是啊，看看这桃树，师傅
I cannot make it blossom when it suits me,
我不能随心所欲催它开花
nor make it bear fruit before its time.
也不能让它提前结出果实
But there are things we can control.
可有些事情是我们能控制的
I can control when the fruit will fall.
我能控制果子什么时候落地
And I can control...
我还能控制⋯
...where to plant the seed.
在哪种下种子
That is no illusion, Master.
这可不是幻想，大师
Yes.
是啊
But no matter what you do
可不论你怎么做
that seed will grow to be a peach tree.
这颗种子都会长成桃树
You may wish for an apple or an orange, but you will get a peach.
你可能想要苹果或桔子 可它只会长成桃子
But a peach cannot defeat Tai Lung!
可一个桃子打不赢大龙！
Maybe it can.
或许它可以
If you are willing to guide it.
如果你愿意引导它
To nurture it.
培育它
To believe in it.
并且相信它
But how? How?
可怎么做？怎么做？
I need your help, Master.
我需要您的指点，大师
No, you just need to believe.
不，你只需要学会相信
Promise me, Shifu.
答应我，师傅
Promise me you will believe.
答应我你会相信他
I will try.
我会⋯努力
Good.
很好
My time has come.
我的时辰到了
You must continue your journey without me.
没有我，你的路也一定要坚持走下去
What are you? Wait!
你这是？等等
Master!
大师！
You can't leave me!
你不能丢下我！
You must believe.
你要学会相信
Master!
大师！
Yeah, so I'm like, "Fine, you may be a wolf,
我就说：“好啊，你是条灰狼”
you may be the scariest bandit in Haijin Province...
“可能还是海锦州人见人怕的大土匪”
...but you're a lousy tipper."
“可给小费却是个铁公鸡”
Really? So how did you get out of there alive?
真的假的？你怎么活着逃出来的？
I mean, I didn't actually say that...
我其实没说出来⋯
...but I thought it...
我也就想想⋯
...in my mind.
心里撒撒气
If he could read my mind, he'd be, like, "What?"
要是他会读心术 肯定问我：“说啥着？”
Order up! Hope you like it.
面条好了！希望你们爱吃
- This is really good! - No, come on.
- 味道真不错！ - 呵呵，别夸我了
Try my dad's Secret Ingredient Soup. He actually knows the secret ingredient.
你应该尝尝我老爸的秘方鲜汤 就他知道秘方
What do you talking about? This is amazing!
你就别谦虚了，这可是极品美味
- You're a really good cook. - I wish my mouth was bigger.
- 你真是好厨子 - 真希望我嘴大点
Tigress, you've got to try this.
娇虎，你得尝尝
It is said that the Dragon Warrior can survive for months on nothing
据说神龙大侠能不吃不喝熬过几个月
but the dew of ginkgo leaf and the energy of the universe.
仅凭银杏叶上的露珠和天地之气
I guess my body doesn't know it's the Dragon Warrior yet.
可能我身体还不知道成了神龙大侠
I'm gonna need a lot more than dew and universe juice.
我可不能只靠露水和什么天地之气
drink soup
喝汤
- What? - Nothing... Master Shifu.
- 怎么了？ - 没什么⋯你像师傅
Never be the Dragon Warrior unless you lose 500 pounds and brush your teeth!
你成为不了神龙大侠 除非你减掉450斤肉，天天刷牙
What is that noise you're making? Laughter? I never heard of it!
你们发什么怪声？笑声？我没听过
Work hard, panda, and maybe someday...
努力点，熊猫，没准哪天⋯
...you will have ears like mine.
你就能有我这样的耳朵
That's good.
学得真像
Ears. It's not working for you? I thought they were pretty good.
耳朵，不好笑吗？我觉得挺有创意的啊
It's Shifu!
是师傅！
Of course it's Shifu. What do you think I'm doing?
当然是师傅，你们以为我在模仿谁？
Master Shifu!
是功夫大师！
You think this is funny?
你们觉得这好玩吗？
Tai Lung has escaped and you're acting like children!
大龙都越狱了，你们还这么孩子气！
- What? - He is coming for the Dragon Scroll,
- 什么？ - 他是来抢神龙秘籍的
and you are the only one who can stop him.
而你是唯一能阻止他的人
And I was saying you got no sense of humor.
我刚说你没幽默细胞
I'm gonna... stop Tai Lung.
我要⋯阻止大龙
What? You're serious? And I have to?
啥？你没开玩笑？非要我？
Master Oogway will stop him, he did it before, he'll do it again.
乌龟大师能阻止他，就像以前一样
Oogway cannot!
乌龟大师不能了！
Not anymore.
永远不能了
Our only hope is the Dragon Warrior.
我们唯一的希望就是神龙大侠了
- The panda? - Yes, the panda!
- 这个熊猫？ - 是的，这个熊猫！
Master, let us stop Tai Lung. This is what you've trained us for.
师傅，让我们去阻止大龙 您训练我们就是为了这个
No! It is not your destiny to defeat Tai Lung.
不，打败大龙不是你们的使命
It is his!
是他的！
Where'd he go?
他哪去了？
You cannot leave! A real warrior never quits.
你不能放弃！真正的大侠绝不放弃！
Watch me.
等着瞧
Come on.
得了吧
How am I supposed to beat Tai Lung? I can't even beat you to the stairs.
我怎么打败大龙啊？我连逃跑都做不到
You will beat him because you are the Dragon Warrior.
你能打败他，因为你是神龙大侠
You don't believe that. You never believed that.
你才不信呢，你就没信过
From the first moment I've got here, you've tried to get rid of me.
从刚开始你就想赶我走
Yes! I was.
我是想过
But now I ask you to trust in your master as I have come to trust in mine.
可现在我要你相信你师傅 就像我相信乌龟大师一样
You're not my master. And I'm not the Dragon Warrior.
你不是我师傅，我也不是神龙大侠
Then why didn't you quit?! You knew I was going to get ride of you, yet you stayed.
那你怎么没放弃？你知道我要赶你走，可你留下了
Yeah, I stayed.
是啊，我是留下了
I stayed because every time you threw a brick at my head
我留下来，是因为就算你拿板砖拍我
or said I smelled, it hurt, but it could never hurt more
或是说我不讲卫生，伤我自尊 可再伤心也比不过⋯
than it did every day of my life just being me.
日复一日发现我还是原来的我
I stayed because I thought, if anyone could change me...
我留下来，因为我觉得就算只有一人能改变我
...could make me... not me...
能够让我脱胎换骨⋯
...it was you.
也该是你
The greatest kung fu teacher in all of China!
全中国最伟大的功夫大师
But I can change you!
可我能改变你！
I can turn you into the Dragon Warrior! And I will!
我能把你变成神龙大侠！我也会的！
Come on. Tai Lung is on his way here right now.
算了吧，大龙马上就杀过来了
Even if it takes him a hundred years to get here, how are you...
就算他花一百年才到这里，你要怎么做⋯
...gonna change this into the Dragon Warrior?
才能把这堆肉变成神龙大侠？
How?
怎么做？
- How?! - I don't know!
- 说啊 - 我不知道！
I don't know.
我不知道⋯
That's what I thought.
我就说么
This is what you trained me for.
你训练我就是为了这个
Tigress!
娇虎！
Don't try and stop me.
别想拦我
We're not trying to stop you.
我们不是要拦你
What?
什么？
We're coming with you!
我们和你并肩作战
What? I eat when I'm upset, OK?
怎么？我一心烦就吃东西解闷，行了吧
No need to explain.
不用解释
I thought you might be Monkey. He hides his almond cookies on the top shelf.
我还以为你是金猴 他把杏仁饼干藏在架子顶层
Don't tell Monkey.
别告诉金猴
- Look at you. - Yeah, I know, I disgust you.
- 瞧瞧你 - 是啊，我知道，又招你讨厌了
No, I mean, how did you get up there?
不是，我是说，你是怎么上去的？
I don't know. I guess that...
我也不知道，我猜就是⋯
I don't know. I was getting a cookie.
不知道，我想要吃饼干着
Yet you are ten feet off the ground.
可你一蹦就离地一丈高
And you have done a perfect spilt.
还来个完美大劈叉
No, this? This is just...
这也算？这是个⋯
...an accident.
意外
There are no accidents.
从来就没有意外
Come with me.
跟我来
I know you're trying to be all mystical and kung fuey...
我知道你们练武的都神叨叨的
...but could you at least tell me where we're going?
可怎么也得告诉我去哪儿啊
You dragged me...
你让我⋯
...all the way out here...
跑这么老远
...for a bath?
为了洗个澡？
Panda...
熊猫
...we do not wash our pits in the Pool of Sacred Tears.
这圣泪池可不是洗胳肢窝用的
The Pool of...
什么池？
This is where Oogway unraveled the mysteries...
乌龟就是在这里解开
...of harmony and focus.
和谐入定的玄机
This is the birthplace of kung fu.
这里是功夫的诞生地
Do you want to learn kung fu?
想学功夫吗？
Yeah!
想！
Then I am your master!
那我就是你的师傅！
OK!
好啊！
Don't cry.
不许哭
OK.
不哭
(personal hygiene)
（毛外套又当抹布了）
When you focus on kung fu,
你专心学武
when you concentrate...
越是专心
...you stink.
学得越烂
Perhaps that is my fault.
这也许是我的失误
I cannot train you the way I have trained the Five.
我不能像训练五侠那样训练你
I now see that the way to get through to you is with this.
我现在找到打通你武学的穴道了，就是用这个
Oh, great, 'cause I am hungry.
啊，太好了，我都饿坏了
Good.
正好
When you have been trained, you may eat.
你训练完了，就可以开吃了
Let us begin.
开始吧
After you, panda.
你先来，熊猫
Just like that?
就这么简单？
No sit-ups? No ten-mile hike?
没仰卧起坐？不用跑30里路？
I vowed to train you, and you have been trained. You are free to eat.
我发过誓训练你，你已经练成了 你可以开吃了
Enjoy.
请吧
Hey!
嘿！
(eat)
吃
I said you are free to eat. Have a dumpling.
我说你可以随便吃，来个包子
Hey!
嘿！
You are free to eat.
随便吃啊
- Am I?! - Are you?!
- 随便吗？ - 你行吗？
I'm not hungry.
我不饿了
Master.
师傅
Cut it!
砍断绳索！
Where's the Dragon Warrior?
神龙大侠在哪儿？
How do you know you're not looking at her?
你怎么知道眼前就不是？
You think I'm a fool?
你当我脑残了啊？
I know you're not the Dragon Warrior. None of you!
我知道你不是神龙大侠，你们都不是
I heard how he fell out of the sky in a ball of fire.
我听说他坐着火球从天而降
That he's a warrior unlike anything the world has ever seen.
世人从没见过他那样的大侠
- Po? - So that is his name. Po.
- 阿宝？ - 原来叫这名儿，阿宝
Finally, a worthy opponent.
总算有个配的上的对手了
Our battle will be legendary!
我们的大战会载入史册
We've got this. Help her.
我们撑着，快去帮她
Monkey!
金猴！
Go!
快去！
What was I thinking?!
我真白忙乎了
Mantis!
螳螂！
Now!
就现在！
Shifu taught you well.
师傅教得不错
But he didn't teach you everything.
可他没全教给你们
You have done well, panda.
你干得很好，熊猫
Done well? Done well?
就很好？只是很好？
I've done awesome!
我很强大！
The mark of a true hero is humility.
真正的英雄懂得谦虚
But, yes, you have done...
不过，你确实⋯
...awesome
很强大
Guys? Guys?! They're dead!
伙计们？都怎么了？他们死了！
No, they're breathing. They're asleep? But their eyes are open.
不，还喘气呢，睡着了？可眼睁着
We were no match for his nerve attach.
我们斗不过他的点穴神功
He's gotten stronger.
他变得更强了
Who? Tai Lung? Stronger?
谁？大龙？更强了？
He's too fast!
他太快了！
Sorry, Po.
对不起，阿宝
I thought we could stop him.
我还以为能阻止他
He could have killed you.
他本可以杀了你们
Why didn't he?
为什么没杀？
So you could come back and strike fear into our hearts. But it won't work.
这样你们就能回来让我们心惊胆颤 可这没用
It might. I mean, a little.
有可能，其实，我有点怕
I'm pretty scared.
我是非常怕啊
You can defeat him, panda!
你能打败他，熊猫！
Are you kidding? If they can't?!
开玩笑吧？虎胆五侠都不行！
They're five masters. I'm just one me.
他们可是五位大侠，而我就一个小胖
But you will have the one thing that no one else does.
可你拥有他们都没有的东西
You really believe I'm ready?
你真认为我准备好了？
You are...
是的
...Po.
阿宝
Behold the Dragon Scroll.
看吧，神龙秘籍
It is yours.
是你的了
Wait. What happens when I read it?
等等，我看了以后会怎么样？
No one knows, but Legend says you will be able to hear a butterfly's wing beat.
据说你能听到蝴蝶拍打翅膀的声音
Really? That's cool.
真的？太酷了！
Yes. And see light in the deepest cave.
是啊，还能在最黑的山洞看到光亮
You will feel the universe in motion around you.
还能感受到天地的运转
Can I punch through walls?
我能打穿墙吗？
- Do a quadruple back flip? - Focus.
- 能做四个后空翻吗？ - 专心点
- Will I? - Focus.
- 能吗？ - 专心
- Focus. - Oh, yeah, yeah.
- 专心 - 啊，好的，好的
Read it, Po, and fulfill your destiny.
读完它，阿宝，去完成你的使命
Read it and become the Dragon Warrior
读完它，你就能成为神龙大侠
It's impossible to open.
怎么打不开啊
OK. Come on, baby. Come on now.
来啊，宝贝，出来啊
Thank you.
谢谢了
I probably loosened it up for you though.
估计是我替你弄松了
OK, here goes.
好，开卷了！
- It's blank. - What?!
- 是空的 - 什么？
- Here, look. - No, I am forbidden to look upon...
- 你自己看 - 不行，按规矩我是不能看⋯
Blank. I don't...
空的，我不⋯
I don't understand.
我不明白
OK. So, like...
好吧，这么看来⋯
...Oogway was just a crazy old turtle after all.
乌龟多半是个老疯子
No. Oogway was wiser than us all.
不，乌龟的智慧我们都比不上
Oh, come on! Face it, he picked me by accident.
得了吧！实际情况是因为意外才选中的我
Of course I'm not the Dragon Warrior. Who am I kidding?
我才不是什么神龙大侠，我骗谁啊
But who will stop Tai Lung?
可谁去阻止大龙呢？
He'll destroy everything and everyone.
他会杀了所有人，毁了一切
No.
不会的
Evacuate the valley. You must protect the villagers from Tai Lung's rage.
撤空和平谷，你们要保护村民不受伤害
- What about you, Master? - I will fight him.
- 可你呢？师傅？ - 我会跟他斗
- What? - I can hold him off long enough
- 什么？ - 我能拖延他一段时间
for everyone to escape.
大家就能逃走了
But, Shifu, he'll kill you.
可师傅，他会杀了你
Then I will finally have paid for my mistake.
那我也算弥补过错了
Listen to me, all of you.
你们听我说
It is time for you to continue your journey without me.
没有我，你们的路也一定要坚持走下去
I am very proud to have been your master.
成为你们的师傅我很自豪
We've got to get them out safely.
咱们得把乡亲们带到安全的地方
Come, little one. Let's find your mama.
过来，小家伙，我带你找妈妈去
Viper, gather the southern farmers. Mantis, the north.
灵蛇，集合南部村民，螳螂，负责北面
Crane, light the way.
仙鹤，提灯领路
Look, it's the Dragon Warrior.
看呐，是神龙大侠
Hey, Dad.
嘿，爸爸
Po!
阿宝！
Good to have you back, son.
你能回来真好，儿子
Good to be back.
我也这么觉得
Let's go, Po.
咱们走吧，阿宝
So for our next shop, it's time to face it...
是该考虑咱们的下一个店铺了
...the future of noodles is dice-cut vegetables...
面条的前景嘛，配菜要切成块
...no longer slices.
不是切成丝
Also, I was thinking, maybe this time
而且，我还琢磨着，这次⋯
we'll have a kitchen you can actually stand up in.
咱们造个大点的厨房，你站直了进去
You like that?
觉得怎么样？
Po, I'm sorry if things didn't work out.
阿宝，你没如愿，我也挺伤心的
It just wasn't meant to be.
可能那就不是你的命
Po, forget everything else.
阿宝，别胡思乱想了
Your destiny still awaits.
还有大好前途等着你呢
We are noodle folk. Broth runs deep through our veins.
我们是做面条的，血脉里流淌着汤汁
I don't know, Dad.
我心里挺乱的，爸爸
Honestly, sometimes I can't believe I'm actually your son.
说实话，有时候我都不相信是你儿子
Po...
阿宝⋯
...I think it's time I told you something I should have told you...
我想是时候该告诉你些事情了
...a long time ago.
我早该跟你说的
OK.
好啊
The secret ingredient of my Secret Ingredient Soup.
我那秘方鲜汤的秘方是
Come here. The secret ingredient is nothing.
离近点，秘方是不加料
You heard me. Nothing!
你听着了，不加料
There is no secret ingredient!
根本就没有什么秘方！
Wait, wait. It's just plain old noodle soup?
等等，就是普通的面汤？
You don't add some kind of special sauce or something?
你不加什么特殊佐料之类的？
Don't have to. To make something special, you just believe it's special.
不用啊，想要让它变得特别 你只要相信它很特别
There is no secret ingredient.
根本就没有什么秘方
I have come home, Master.
我回家了，师傅
This is no longer your home. And I am no longer your master.
这里不再是你的家，我也不再是你的师傅
Oh, yes. You have a new favorite.
噢，是啊，你收了个新宝贝
So where is this Po?
这个阿宝在哪儿？
Did I scare him off?
我给他吓跑了？
This battle is between you and me.
这战斗是你我之间的
So, that is how it's going to be.
那我就奉陪好了
That is how it must be.
咱们必须了结
I rotted in jail for 20 years because of your weakness!
我蹲了20年大牢，都是因为你太软弱！
Obeying your master is not weakness!
服从师傅不是软弱！
You knew I was the Dragon Warrior.
你早知道我就是神龙大侠
You always knew.
你早知道
But when Oogway said otherwise, what did you do?
可乌龟拒绝的时候，你做什么了？
What did you do?!
帮我了吗？
Nothing!
没有！
You were not meant to be the Dragon Warrior! That was not my fault!
你命中注定不是神龙大侠！那不是我的错！
Not your fault?!
不是你的错？
Who filled my head with dreams?!
是谁让我心怀美梦？
Who drove me to train until my bones cracked?!
又是谁让我训练得伤筋断骨？！
Who denied me my destiny?!
是谁阻挡了我的命运？！
It was never my decision to make!
这我没有权利决定
It is now.
现在有了
Give me the scroll!
把秘籍交出来！
I would rather die.
我宁愿去死
All I ever did, I did to make you proud!
我所作的一切，都是为了让你自豪！
Tell me how proud you are, Shifu!
告诉我你有多自豪，师傅！
Tell me!
告诉我！
I have... I have always been proud of you.
我⋯我一直都为你自豪
From the first moment, I've been proud of you.
从一开始，你就是我的骄傲
And it was my pride that blinded me.
可我的骄傲让我丧失了判断
I loved you too much to see what you were becoming...
我过于爱你，没有看清你
what I was turning you into.
是我让你走上了歧途
I'm, I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
I don't want your apology.
我不要你道歉！
I want my scroll!
我要我的秘籍！
What?!
什么？！
Where is it?!
它哪去了？！
Dragon Warrior has taken the scroll halfway across China by now.
神龙大侠已经带着秘籍远走高飞了
You will never see that scroll, Tai Lung.
你永远别想得到它，大龙
Never.
永远
Stairs.
爬楼真累
Who are you?
你又是谁？
Buddy, I am the Dragon Warrior.
伙计，我是⋯神龙大侠
You?
你？
Him? He's a panda.
他？他是个熊猫
You're a panda. What are you gonna do, big guy? Sit on me?
你是个熊猫，想怎么着胖胖？一屁股坐死我？
Don't tempt me.
别惹火了我
No. I'm gonna use this.
算了，我会用这个
You want it? Come and get it.
想要吗？来拿啊
Finally!
总算到手了！
That scroll is mine!
秘籍是我的！
Lightning!
快如闪电！
The scroll has given him power!
秘籍给了他力量
No!
不！
Finally! Oh, yes.
总算！太棒了
The power of the Dragon Scroll is mine!
秘籍的力量归我了！
It's nothing!
什么都没有
It's OK. I didn't get it the first time, either.
没关系的，头一次我也没弄明白
What?
什么？
There is no secret ingredient.
根本就没有什么秘方
It's just you.
关键在自己
Stop it!
停下
I'm gonna pee.
我都要尿了
Don't. Don't! Don't!
不要嘛！ 不要
You can't defeat me.
你不可能打败我
You, you're just a big fat panda
你就是个大胖熊猫！
I'm not a big fat panda.
我不是普通的大胖熊猫
I'm the big fat panda.
我是传奇的大胖熊猫
The Wuxi Finger Hold!
五溪劫指扣！
Oh, you know this hold?
你知道这招？
You're bluffing. You're bluffing. Shifu didn't teach you that.
你吹牛，你在吹牛，师傅才不会教你呢
Nope.
是不会
I figured it out. Skadoosh.
我无师自通的，再见吧
Look!
快看！
The Dragon Warrior.
神龙大侠
That's my boy! That big lovely kung fu warrior is my son!
是我孩子！这个可爱的功夫大侠是我儿子
Yes!
好孩子！
Thanks, Dad.
谢谢，爸爸
Hey, guys.
嘿，伙计们
Master. Master.
大师. 大师
Master?
大师？
Master Shifu!
咱们师傅！
Master!
师傅！
Shifu, are you OK?!
师傅，你没事吧？！
Po.
阿宝
You're alive.
你还活着
Or we're both dead.
还是咱们都死了？
No, Master, I didn't die. I defeated Tai Lung.
不，师傅，我没死，我打败大龙了
You did?
打败了？
It is as Oogway foretold.
跟乌龟预言的一样
You are the Dragon Warrior.
你就是神龙大侠
You have brought peace to this valley
你把安宁带给了山谷
and ... and to me.
也给了我
Thank you.
谢谢
Thank you, Po.
谢谢，阿宝
Thank you. Thank you.
谢谢你，谢谢
No! Master! No, no, no, don't die, Shifu, please!
不！师傅！不不不，师傅别死啊！
I'm not dying, you idiot!
我没死，你个白痴！
Dragon Warrior...
哦，是神龙大侠⋯
...I am simply at peace. Finally.
我只是静心了，总算静心了
So, I should stop talking?
那，我不该说话了？
If you can.
最好别说
Want to get something to eat?
想吃点东西吗？
Yeah.
好吧
(fun stuff coming ahead)
【还有精彩内容，不妨看到最后】
Everybody is kung fu fighting
∮大家都在用功拼搏
Your mind becomes fast as lightning
∮而你思维快若闪电
Although the future is a little bit frightening
∮虽然前路有些迷茫
It's the book of your life that you're writing
∮可你还是去书写生命篇章
Everybody is kung fu fighting
∮大家都在用功拼搏
Your mind becomes fast as lightning
∮而你思维快若闪电
Although the future is a little bit frightening
∮虽然前路有些迷茫
It's the book of your life that you're writing
∮可你还是去书写生命篇章
You are a natural
∮你是天生功夫大侠
Why is that so hard to see?
∮却又长久迷失自我
Maybe it's just because You keep on looking at me
∮可能因为太过关注眼前
The journey's a lonely one So much more than we know
∮旅途比我们想得更加孤单
But sometimes you've got to go And be your own hero
∮可有时得站出来成为自己的英雄
Everybody is kung fu fighting
∮大家都在用功拼搏
Your mind becomes fast as lightning
∮而你思维快若闪电
Although the future is a little bit frightening
∮虽然前路有些迷茫
It's the book of your life that you're writing
∮可你还是去书写生命篇章
You're a diamond in the rough A brilliant ball of clay
∮你是泥中钻石沙中金子
You could be a work of art If you just go all the way
∮一往无前就能成为造化杰作
Now what would it take to break? I believe that you can bend
∮碰到困难？用心突破
Not only do you have to fight But you have got to win
∮不仅要战，还要胜利
'Cause everybody is kung fu fighting
∮因为大家都在用功拼搏
Your mind becomes fast as lightning
∮而你思维快若闪电
Although the future is a little bit frightening
∮虽然前路有些迷茫
It's the book of your life that you're writing
∮可你还是去书写生命篇章
You're a diamond in the rough A brilliant ball of clay
【灵蛇被扎成了神龙大侠】 ∮你是泥中钻石沙中金子
You could be a work of art If you just go all the way
∮一往无前就能成为造化杰作
Now what would it take to break? I believe that you can bend
∮碰到困难？用心突破
Not only do you have to fight But you have got to win
∮不仅要战，还要胜利
'Cause everybody is kung fu fighting
∮因为大家都在用功拼搏
Your mind becomes fast as lightning
【金猴的饼干都被阿宝偷吃光了】 ∮而你思维快若闪电
Although the future is a little bit frightening
∮虽然前路有些迷茫
It's the book of your life that you're writing
∮可你还是去书写生命篇章
(about panda)
熊猫每天最少要花10个小时以上吃东西，最少吃20多斤
(about the restaurant)
电影中在小黑板写过饭馆特色：麻辣烫面、自制干面
(Shifu plays poorly on Chinese Chess )
【阿宝拉面待客，平先生象棋狂切功夫大师】
(about Mantis)
螳螂最早曾被设计成和大龙密谋的大反派
(about crane)
电影中仙鹤共有6019片羽毛
(about monkey)
金猴由成龙配音
(Demon Mountain continued)
【阿宝大闹恶魔山】
(reveal the scroll to the young citizens)
【神龙秘籍之幼儿精讲班】
(about viper)
电影中蛇身上共设计了120块骨头
(where are the peaches?)
【还想着吃桃子呢⋯】
(about Oogway)
乌龟成仙化作37517片花瓣，场景历时6个月制作完成
(laughter?never heard before?)
【娇虎和师傅都不再一本正经了】
(poor Zeng fixing up the Urn)
【小善负责把阿宝打碎的灵坛粘好】
(about shifu)
功夫大师是只小熊猫，最早设计中师傅还带个眼镜
(about tailong)
大龙是只雪豹
(the owner and the action figure himself)
【阿宝终于有了一个玩具娃娃的自己】
(about the movie)
08年11月会发行《虎胆五侠的秘密》讲述他们的来历
(growing seed)
【栽下的桃核已经长成幼苗啦】
THE END
剧终